Today I'm going to talk about work.
سأتكلم اليوم عن العمل .
And the question I want to ask and answer is this:
و السؤال الذي سأطرحه و أجيب عليه هو :
"Why do we work?"
لماذا نعمل ؟
Why do we drag ourselves out of bed every morning
لماذا نجر أنفسنا من السرير كل صباح
instead of living our lives
بدلاً من أن نعيش حياتنا
just filled with bouncing from one TED-like adventure to another?
ممتلئة بقفزات من مغامرات كـ "TED" لأخرى
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
You may be asking yourselves that very question.
قد تسألون أنفسكم هذا السؤال هذا السؤال بالذات .
Now, I know of course, we have to make a living,
أعلم الآن بالطبع أنه علينا أن نغطي معايشنا ،
but nobody in this room thinks that that's the answer to the question,
ولكن لا أحد في هذه القاعة يعتقد أن هذه إجابة للسؤال ،
"Why do we work?"
"لماذا نعمل ؟"
For folks in this room, the work we do is challenging,
بالنسبة لأغلب الناس في هذه القاعة العمل الذي نقوم به مليء بالتحديات،
it's engaging, it's stimulating, it's meaningful.
يشغلك ، يحفزك وهو ذا معنى .
And if we're lucky, it might even be important.
و إذا كنا محظوظين قد يكون مهما جدا .
So, we wouldn't work if we didn't get paid,
و كذلك ، لن نعمل إذا لم يُدفع لنا ،
but that's not why we do what we do.
لكن هذا ليس سبب ان نفعل ما نفعله .
And in general,
و بشكل عام ،
I think we think that material rewards are a pretty bad reason
أعتقد اننا نظن أن العوائد المادية سبب سخيف
for doing the work that we do.
للقيام بالعمل الذي نعمله .
When we say of somebody that he's "in it for the money,"
عندما نقول عن شخص "إنه يعمل من أجل المال."
we are not just being descriptive.
لن نكون وصفيين فحسب
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Now, I think this is totally obvious,
اعتقد الآن ان هذا واضح تماماً ،
but the very obviousness of it raises what is for me
و لكن الاكثر وضوحا يثير ماهو بالنسبة لي
an incredibly profound question.
سؤال عميق بشكلٍ لا يصدق ،
Why, if this is so obvious,
لماذا .. اذا كان هذا واضحا جدا ،
why is it that for the overwhelming majority of people on the planet,
لماذا الأغلبية العظمى من الناس على هذا الكوكب ،
the work they do has none of the characteristics
يقومون بالعمل بدون الخصائص
that get us up and out of bed and off to the office every morning?
التي تجعلهم يستيقظون و ينهضون من السرير و يذهبون للمكتب كل صباح ؟
How is it that we allow the majority of people on the planet
كيف لنا ان نتيح ذلك لأغلبية الناس على الكوكب
to do work that is monotonous, meaningless and soul-deadening?
للقيام بعمل ممل و بلا معنى و مميت للروح ؟
Why is it that as capitalism developed,
لماذا كان كالرأسمالية المطورة
it created a mode of production, of goods and services,
خلقت نمط لإنتاج السلع و الخدمات
in which all the nonmaterial satisfactions that might come from work were eliminated?
بحيث يكون كل الرضا الروحي الذي قد يأتي من عمل ، منبوذ ؟
Workers who do this kind of work,
العمال الذين يقومون بهذا النوع من العمل
whether they do it in factories, in call centers,
سواء كانوا يقومون بهذا في المصانع ، في مراكز الإتصال ،
or in fulfillment warehouses,
أو في المستودعات ،
do it for pay.
يقومون به مقابل أجر .
There is certainly no other earthly reason to do what they do except for pay.
بالتاكيد ليس هناك أي سبب دنيوي لفعل هذا ماعدا الأجر .
So the question is, "Why?"
لذا السؤال هو : " لماذ؟"
And here's the answer:
و هنا الإجابة :
the answer is technology.
الإجابة هي: التكنولوجيا .
Now, I know, I know --
أعلم ..أعلم ..
yeah, yeah, yeah, technology, automation screws people, blah blah --
أجل .. أجل تكنولوجيا و تشغيل ذاتي يخدع الناس و..و..
that's not what I mean.
ليس هذا مأعنيه ،
I'm not talking about the kind of technology
انا لا أتحدث عن نوع التكنولوجيا
that has enveloped our lives, and that people come to TED to hear about.
التي غطت حياتنا فيأتي الناس إلى ( TED ) للإستماع لها .
I'm not talking about the technology of things,
انا لا أتحدث عن تكنولوجية الأشياء ،
profound though that is.
رغما عن أهمية ذلك.
I'm talking about another technology.
أنا أتحدث عن تكنولوجيا أخرى ..
I'm talking about the technology of ideas.
أتحدث عن تكنولوجية الأفكار .
I call it, "idea technology" --
أسميها " تكنولوجيا الفكرة "
how clever of me.
كم أنا ذكي .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
In addition to creating things, science creates ideas.
بالأضافة إلى خلق الأشياء تقوم العلوم بخلق أفكار .
Science creates ways of understanding.
تخلق العلوم طرق التفاهم .
And in the social sciences,
و في العلوم الإجتماعية ،
the ways of understanding that get created are ways of understanding ourselves.
وسائل التفاهم التي نشأت هي طرق لفهم أنفسنا .
And they have an enormous influence on how we think, what we aspire to,
و لها تأثير هائل على كيف نفكر فيما نطمح إليه ،
and how we act.
و كيف نتصرف .
If you think your poverty is God's will, you pray.
إذا كنت تعتقد أن فقرك هو مشيئة الله ، تصلي .
If you think your poverty is the result of your own inadequacy,
إذا كت تعتقد أن فقرك نتيجة عدم كفائتك ،
you shrink into despair.
ستشعر باليأس .
And if you think your poverty is the result of oppression and domination,
وإذا كنت تعتقد أن فقرك هو نتيجة القمع والهيمنة ،
then you rise up in revolt.
فإنك ستتمرد في ثورة .
Whether your response to poverty is resignation or revolution,
سواء أجبتم على الفقر بأنه استسلام أو ثورة ،
depends on how you understand the sources of your poverty.
يعتمد على مدى فهمكم لمصدر فقركم .
This is the role that ideas play in shaping us as human beings,
هذا الدور الذي تلعبه الأفكار في تشكيلنا على هيئة بشر ،
and this is why idea technology may be the most profoundly important technology
و هذا سبب أن تكنولوجيا الفكرة قد تكون أعمق وأهم تكنولوجيا
that science gives us.
تمنحنا اياها العلوم .
And there's something special about idea technology,
و هناك شيء مميز عن تكنولوجيا الفكرة ،
that makes it different from the technology of things.
الذي يجعلها تختلف عن تكنولوجيا الأشياء ،
With things, if the technology sucks,
في حالة الأشياء اذا فشلت التكنولوجيا
it just vanishes, right?
ستختفي ، صحيح ؟
Bad technology disappears.
التكنولوجيا السيئة تختفي .
With ideas --
في حالة الأفكار ،
false ideas about human beings will not go away
الأفكار الخاطئة عن البشر لن تخفي
if people believe that they're true.
إذا اعتقد اناس أنهم على صواب
Because if people believe that they're true,
لأن الناس اذا اعتقدوا انهم على صواب
they create ways of living and institutions
سيخلقون وسائل عيش و مؤسسات
that are consistent with these very false ideas.
تنسجم مع هذه الأفكار الخاطئة جداً .
And that's how the industrial revolution created a factory system
وبهذه طريقة أنشأت الثورة الصناعية نظام صناعي
in which there was really nothing you could possibly get out of your day's work,
حيث لا شي حقيقي يمكنك ان تحصل عليه في يوم عملك ،
except for the pay at the end of the day.
ماعدا الأجر في نهاية اليوم .
Because the father -- one of the fathers
بسبب واحد من آباء
of the Industrial Revolution, Adam Smith --
الثور الصناعية آدم سميث
was convinced that human beings were by their very natures lazy,
كان مقتنعاً بأن البشر كانوا بطبعهم كسولين جدا ،
and wouldn't do anything unless you made it worth their while,
و كانوا لا يفعلون شيئاً ماعدا مايستحق وقتهم ،
and the way you made it worth their while
و الطريقة التي تجعله يستحق وقتهم
was by incentivizing, by giving them rewards.
كانت عن طريق التحفيز بإعطائهم مكافآت ،
That was the only reason anyone ever did anything.
التي كانت السبب الوحيد في أن يفعل اي شخص أي شيء .
So we created a factory system consistent with that false view of human nature.
لذا قمنا بعمل نظام صناعي متسق مع هذه النظرة الخاطئة لطبيعة البشر .
But once that system of production was in place,
ولكن بمجرد أن كان نظام الإنتاج هذا في مكان ما ،
there was really no other way for people to operate,
لم يكن هناك وسيلة أخرى للناس للعمل حقا ،
except in a way that was consistent with Adam Smith's vision.
ماعدا بالطريقة الثابتة حسب رؤية أدم سميث .
So the work example is merely an example
لذلك مثال العمل هو مجرد مثال
of how false ideas can create a circumstance
لكيف يمكن للأفكار الخاطئة أن تكون ظرفاً
that ends up making them true.
لكي ينتهي به الأمر لجعل الفكرة صائبة .
It is not true
ليس صحيحاً
that you "just can't get good help anymore."
أنك لا تستطيع الحصول على وسائل جيدة بعد الآن .
It is true
الصحيح
that you "can't get good help anymore"
أنك " لا تستطيع الحصول على وسائل جيدة بعد الآن "
when you give people work to do that is demeaning and soulless.
عندما تمنح الناس عملاً يعتبر مهينا و بلا روح لينجزوه .
And interestingly enough, Adam Smith --
و المثير للآنتباه آدم سميث
the same guy who gave us this incredible invention
نفس الرجل الذي قدم لنا هذا الإختراع المذهل
of mass production, and division of labor
للإنتاج الضخم و تقسيم العماله
-- understood this.
فهم هذا .
He said, of people who worked in assembly lines,
قال انه من الناس الذين عملوا في خطوط التجميع
of men who worked in assembly lines, he says:
من الرجال الذين عملوا في خطوط التجميع، يقول
"He generally becomes as stupid as it is possible for a human being to become."
"انه يصبح بشكل عام غبي بالشكل الممكن للإنسان أن يصبح عليه ".
Now, notice the word here is "become."
الآن لاحظوا كلمة "يصبح."
"He generally becomes as stupid as it is possible for a human being to become."
"انه يصبح بشكل عام غبي بالشكل الممكن للإنسان أن يصبح عليه ."
Whether he intended it or not, what Adam Smith was telling us there,
سواءً قصد هذا أم لا ما يخبرنا به (آدم سميث)
is that the very shape of the institution within which people work
هو تشكيل المؤسسة مع الاشخاص العاملين
creates people who are fitted to the demands of that institution
و تشكيل الناس المناسبين لمطالب تلك المؤسسة
and deprives people of the opportunity
و حرمان بعض الناس من الفرصة
to derive the kinds of satisfactions from their work that we take for granted.
للحصول علي اشكال من الرضا عن أعمالهم ، ما نعتبره أمر مسُلّم به .
The thing about science -- natural science --
هذا الأمر بشأن العلوم العلوم الأجتماعية
is that we can spin fantastic theories about the cosmos,
هو أننا نستطيع حبك النظريات المذهلة حول النظام
and have complete confidence
و نحصل على الثقة الكاملة
that the cosmos is completely indifferent to our theories.
ذلك ان النظام يختلف تماما مع نظرياتنا .
It's going to work the same damn way
سوف يعمل بنفس الطريقة اللعينة
no matter what theories we have about the cosmos.
لا يهم ما لدينا من نظريات حول النظام .
But we do have to worry about the theories we have of human nature,
لكن علينا القلق بشأن النظريات التي نملكها بشأن طبيعة البشر
because human nature will be changed by the theories we have
لأن طبيعة البشر ستتغير عن طريق النظريات التي نملكها
that are designed to explain and help us understand human beings.
التي صممت لشرح و مساعدتنا في فهم طبيعة البشر .
The distinguished anthropologist, Clifford Geertz, said, years ago,
الانثروبولوجي المميز ( كليفورد غيرتز ) قال قبل سنوات :
that human beings are the "unfinished animals."
البشر هم : "الحيوانات الغير منتهية ."
And what he meant by that was that it is only human nature
و المقصد من ذلك كان الطبيعة الأنسانية
to have a human nature
أن تمتلك الطبيعة الإنسانية
that is very much the product of the society in which people live.
هذا بحدٍ كبير نتيجة المجتمع الذي يعيش فيه الناس.
That human nature, that is to say our human nature,
ذلك أن الطبيعة الإنسانية لتقول أن طبيعتنا البشرية
is much more created than it is discovered.
مخلوقة أكثر من كونها مكتشفة .
We design human nature
لقد شكلنا طبيعة البشر
by designing the institutions within which people live and work.
عن طريق تشكيل المؤسسات حسب ما يعيشه الناس و ما يعملون .
And so you people --
و كذلك أنتم أيها الناس
pretty much the closest I ever get to being with masters of the universe --
تقريبا اكثر الاشخاص قربا فيمن وجدت لتكونوا سادة العالم
you people should be asking yourself a question,
انتم ايها الناس يجب أن تسألوا أنفسكم سؤالاً
as you go back home to run your organizations.
عند عودتكم منازلكم لتديروا مؤسساتكم.
Just what kind of human nature do you want to help design?
مانوع طبيعة البشر التي ترغبون في تشكيلها ؟
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks.
شكراً